Journal of Abnormal Psychology
1965, Vol. 70, No. 3, 218-220

VOICE QUALITY IN DEPRESSION 1
WILLIAM A. HARGREAVES[BMS1], J. A. STARKWEATHER[BMS2], AND K. H. BLACKER
Langley Porter Neuropsychiatric Institute and The University of California School of Medicine

32 depressed patients were interviewed daily throughout their hospitalization. Spectrum analyses of the patients' speech were compared with mood ratings made by the 2 clinicians who jointly conducted the interviews. Using a step­ wise multiple regression with cross-validation for each patient, predictions of
the mood ratings from the voice spectra correlated significantly (1% level)
with the ratings for 25 of the 32 patients. These cross-validation correlations were largest for those patients who showed considerable change in their mood.


  Severe depression is accompanied by a variety of behavioral changes. The clinician may see changes in patterns of movement and speech, in postural and facial indications of apathy or anxiety, and changes in the thought content reported by the person. While there has been recent interest in developing system­ atic rating techniques to assess depression (Beck, Ward, Mendelson, Mock, & Erbaugh, 1961; Grinker, Miller, Sabshin, Nunn, & Nunnally, 1961; Hamilton & White, 1959;
Hamilton, 1960; Overall, 1962; Wechsler, Grosser, & Busfield, 1963), very little has been attempted in the way of direct measure­ ment of the behavior of depressed patients. Furthermore, most of the attention in current studies of depressive symptomatology is given to differentiating groups of patients, while relatively little attention is given to detailed measurement of change in patients over time. We have explored a method of measuring voice quality, the sound of the voice rather than the content. Changes in voice quality frequently	accompany	depression,	and measurement of these changes is a first step toward the comprehensive measurement of depressive symptoms. The voice changes, as with other behavioral changes in depression, are easily observable, but not so easy for the observer to record reliably, or remember well enough to make accurate comparisons over long periods of time. Direct measurement of these symptoms will provide potentially valu-
   1 Presented at Western Psychological Association, Portland, April 1964. This investigation was sup­ ported by Research Grant MH-03375 from the National Institute of Mental Health, United States Public Health Service, and additionally assisted by Public Health Service Research Grant FR-00122.

able criterion measures in studies of the treatment of depression.

METHOD
  The subjects were 32 depressed patients hospital­ ized on the Acute Treatment Service at the Langley Porter Neuropsychiatric Institute. The group con­ sisted of 23 women and 9 men, ranging in age from 20 to 72. Their hospital stay was typically about 5 weeks. A psychiatrist (KHB) and psychologist (WAH) jointly interviewed the patients each day they were in the hospital. The interviews lasted 5 to
10 minutes. The interview began with a question about how the patient felt that day, and after 4 or 5 minutes of inquiry about feelings, concluded with a few standard questions aimed at the assessment of confusion and memory loss, since most of these patients were receiving some kind of somatic therapy.
  The interviews were recorded with an Electrovoice 649A lavalier microphone hung about the patient's neck and throat microphones for the two inter­ viewers. The combined output of the two throat microphones was recorded on a second channel of the tape, providing a clear indication of when anyone but the patient was speaking. At the end of each session the two interviewers rated the patient on an inventory designed for the study, which in­ cluded items related to mood and to confusion and memory loss. Individual items were rated on a scale from zero ("not at all") to eight ("extremely"), although the raters extended the scale when it seemed required by the patient's behavior. The original rating inventory was revised after the first 13 patients to include many items from the Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (Overall & Gorham, 1962). From each version of the inventory, a group of items was combined to yield an overall mood rating for each interview. In the initial version of the inventory the items were rationally selected, while for the revised inventory the item selection was based on a factor analysis of the items. For this item analysis, the third, middle, and third from last interview ratings were selected from each of the 19 subjects. Scores from the two raters were com­ bined. A principal component analysis extracted six

218

VOICE QUALITY IN DEPRESSION	219


factors which were rotated by both the varimax and quartimax methods. The two rotations yielded virtually identical results, indicating a group of items which could form an internally homogeneous scale of mood. These were all items taken from the Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale. Listed in the order of rotated factor loadings, they were the items "depres­ sive mood," "anxiety," "motor retardation," "ten­ sion," and "guilt feelings." For each of the 32 subjects the scores on the mood items were summed for each rater separately, and the interrater agree­ ment across interviews was calculated. This reli­ ability ranged from .51 to • .99, except for one patient who showed little mood change, on whom agreement dropped to .34. The median interrater correlation was .84.
  In analyzing the recordings our task was to dis­ cover what, if any, measurable changes occurred in the sound of the patient's voice when he was depressed. Some obvious things to look for are whether the patient talks loudly or softly, with a high voice or a low voice, with a smooth voice or a harsh voice. Characteristics like these are reflected in the power spectrum of the voice. The voice can be thought of as a mixture of tones of different pitch, with a fundamental pitch at the low end and a series of higher overtones. Just as the timbre of musical instruments corresponds to the way in which various overtones are emphasized, so does voice quality depend upon which overtones in the voice are emphasized. The voice spectrum is a direct measure of the relative prominence in the voice of the fundamental pitch and the various higher overtones. The spectrometer used in this study (Hargreaves & Starkweather, 1963) receives the recorded sound of the patient's voice from the tape-recorder playback, and produces a set of num­ bers on punch cards representing the voice spectrum. Editing in the computer then produces an average spectrum for each consecutive 5 seconds of the patient's speech.

RESULTS AND DISCUSSION
  We did not expect the same kind of de­ pressed voice quality in every subject. There­ fore it was appropriate to study each patient's voice to discover his own particular pattern of change. A multiple-regression procedure was used to develop a method of predicting the mood ratings from the voice spectra of a particular patient. The regression weights were computed using only spectra from even­ numbered interviews. The obtained multiple correlations, one for each patient, ranged from
.57 to .97, with a median of .83. The spectra from the odd-numbered interviews were then used to cross-validate the regression weights. The mood predictions computed from these additional spectra were correlated with the


mood ratings for those interviews. In 25 out of 32 patients these cross-validation cor­ relations were significant at the .01 level or beyond. While this means that for 25 pa­ tients some aspect of the voice changed with mood, it does not mean that the mood ratings could be accurately predicated in all of these patients. Several correlations were about .80, but in other patients the relationship, while statistically significant, was too weak to be of any practical significance.
  The size of the cross-validation correlation was related to how much change occurred in the patient's symptoms. That is, the more the patient's mood changed while he was in the hospital, the more clearly we could see changes in his voice. The variability of the subjects' mood ratings correlated .61 with the size of the cross-validation correlation. If mood neither improved nor worsened sub­ stantially, then it was naturally more diffi­ cult either to see changes in the voice or to obtain reliable ratings of mood change.
  The voice changes found do not appear to be an artifact related to the effects of somatic treatment, though we could not experimentally control these variables. Most of these de­ pressed patients were treated with amitri­ ptyline (Elavil), and some also received a course of six to eight ECT. Amitriptyline dosage was as high as 250 milligrams per day for some patients, and several showed mild confusional reactions while on the drug. The ECT often produced a pronounced confusional reaction. Multiple regression of the voice spectra onto the daily ratings of confusion were computed. Eighteen of the 32 patients had significant cross-validation correlations, suggesting that this type of organic impair­ ment may be reflected in the voice of some patients. These 18 patients did not, however, have higher mood-voice correlations than the remaining 14 patients, the mean correlation being .41 in both groups. The drug regimen of these patients was quite variable, which made it difficult to assess drug effects on the voice. Drug dose per day occasionally correlated highly with rated mood, negatively as often as positively. Therefore any drug effect on the voice could have spuriously produced a mood­ voice relationship. However, patients with high drug-mood correlations did not have a

220	w. A. HARGREAVES, J. A. STARKWEATHER, AND K. H.  BLACKER


greater tendency to show a significant mood­ voice relationship. Furthermore, in a previous study of drug effects on the voice (Stark­ weather & Hargreaves, 1964) we found no clear effects of 150 milligrams of pentobarbital on the voice spectrum, even though audible slurring occurred in several subjects. While these considerations make it unlikely that drug effects account for our findings, further work in this area would benefit from system­ atic control of medication and ECT.
  Is there anything like a typical voice quality of depression? Since the clearest picture of this could be obtained from the patients who showed large changes, we ex­ amined the kinds of voice changes which occurred in 10 patients with large cross­ validation correlations. Five of these showed a depressed voice reduced in loudness and often lacking in high overtones, giving their voice a dull, lifeless quality with diminished inflection. Their quiet voice did not always drop in fundamental frequency, but sometimes rose in frequency in a kind of pathetic whimper. In addition there were 2 or 3 pa­ tients who showed a depressed voice which was actually louder during depression, and sometimes higher in pitch.
  Recent factor analytic studies ( Grinker et al., 1961; Hamilton, 1960; Overall, 1962) have found symptom clusters which may relate to these various types of voice change.

As we become clearer about the types of change which occur, it should be possible to develop ways to measure directly some of these clusters of depressive symptoms. The more prominent symptoms should yield fairly soon to these direct measurement techniques.
REFERENCES
BECK, A. T., WARD, C. H., MENDELSON, M., MocK,
J., & ERBAUGH, J. An inventory for measuring depression. Archives. of General Psychiatry, 1961, 4, 561-571.
GRINKER, R. R., MILLER, J., SABSHIN, M., NUNN, R.,
& NUNNALLY, J. C. The phenomena of depressions.
New York: Harper, 1961.
HAMILTON, M. A rating scale for depression. Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery, and Psychiatry, 1960, 23, 56-62.
HAMILTON, M., & Wurm, J. M. Clinical syndromes in depressive states. Journal of Mental Science, 1959, 105, 985-998.
HARGREAVES, w. A., & STARKWEATHER, J. A. Recogni­
tion of speaker identity. Language and Speech,
1963, 6, 63-67.
OVERALL, J. E. Dimensions of manifest depression. Journal of Psychiatric Research, 1962, 1, 239-245. OVERALL, J. E., & GORHAM, D. R. The brief psy­
chiatric rating scale. Psychological Reports, 1962,
10, 799-812.
STARKWEATHER, J. A., & HARGREAVES, W. A. The
influence of sodium pentobarbital on vocal be­ havior. Journal of Abnormal and Social Psy­ chology, 1964, 69, 123-126.
WECHSLER, H., GROSSER, G. H., & BusFIELD, B. L.
JR. The depression rating scale. Archives of Gen­ eral Psychiatry, 1963, 9, 334-343.
(Received May 13, 1964)
[BMS1]UCSF https://chc.ucsf.edu/people/william-hargreaves-phd
[BMS2]University of California School of Medicine
